<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Susan's Math Games</title><link>susansmathgames/</link><description>Recent content on Susan's Math Games</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2015 23:49:15 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="susansmathgames/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Five-piece tangrams</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/five-piece-tangrams/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 May 2019 23:47:24 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/five-piece-tangrams/</guid><description>These puzzles are very popular with students from kindergarten through grade 3. Having only five pieces instead of the classic seven makes them much less intimidating for many people. Students who enjoy these puzzles may be encouraged to try the classic tangrams.
Making the pieces I use craft foam because it is easy to handle and lasts very well, but if you are in a hurry, you could make them out of cardstock.</description></item><item><title>Streamers</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/streamers/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 May 2019 04:32:43 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/streamers/</guid><description>Streamers has been popular with everyone from grade 4 on up. Here are the demonstration puzzlesto help you get started.
To play, each student will need a set of 16 pieces: squares, triangles, circles, and rhombuses each in blue, green, orange and purple.
Here are the puzzles themselves: 1&amp;amp;2, 3&amp;amp;4, 5&amp;amp;6, 7&amp;amp;8, 9&amp;amp;10, 11&amp;amp;12</description></item><item><title>Classroom introductions</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/classroom-introductions/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2016 00:22:25 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/classroom-introductions/</guid><description>Introducing the class to a puzzle Here&amp;rsquo;s a technique that works for most of the activities in the Puzzles section of this site:
I start by showing the class a completed puzzle and ask them to figure out what the rules must be. This is a lot of fun &amp;ndash; even the youngest students are very good at hunting for patterns. (Where appropriate in these pages, I&amp;rsquo;ve included &amp;ldquo;demos&amp;rdquo; with each type of puzzle.</description></item><item><title>Home</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/home-2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2015 23:49:15 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/home-2/</guid><description>This is math? Encouraging the development of mathematical thinking through play… Newas of May 2019  </description></item><item><title>Towers</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/towers/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2015 04:10:43 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/towers/</guid><description>This is a wonderful puzzle which requires a person to think in three dimensions. Most people seem to find it easier (and more fun) to start by working with physical pieces on a grid. I’ve introduced it to classes as young as grade 5, and to individual students younger than that.
 Here are:
a description of pieces and a template for the grid the process I use to introduce Towersto a group, which you might also use to help you figure it out for yourself the step-by-step solutionfor the example in the introduction a set of Easy 4×4 puzzles,which can be solved using the blocks a set of Medium 4×4 puzzles, which can also be solved using the blocks a set of Hard 4×4 puzzles, for which you might want to get out a pencil and eraser, although they can be solved using the blocks a set of Easy 5×5 puzzles  I’ll post more 5×5 puzzles soon!</description></item><item><title>Magnets</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/magnets/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2015 00:38:12 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/magnets/</guid><description>Here is another solved puzzle, and here is a description of the rules together with a very easy worked example.
A great way to learn to play Magnets is to use physical pieces, as shown in the photo.
Here are:
a description of what’s needed a set of easy puzzles (and solutions) a set of medium puzzles (and solutions) a set of more difficult puzzles (and solutions) If you would like examples of some useful types of logic, here is a step-by-step solution for an easy puzzle and one for a medium puzzle.</description></item><item><title>Set</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/set/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Sep 2014 21:24:14 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/set/</guid><description>This is a wonderful game with many variations and lots of underlying mathematical ideas. It can be played cooperatively or competitively – or both, by working together in teams to compete with other teams. Children often master the rules more quickly than do adults, which adds to their fun.
Here’s a brief outline of the way I introduce the gameto people from about 8 years old to 80. If you would prefer a much more detailed approach, with many examples, go to page 30 of the Nov 2016 issueof The Variable.</description></item><item><title>Computer-related</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/computer-related/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2014 23:54:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/computer-related/</guid><description>Digital pictures Have you ever wondered how computers and all things digital handle pictures? This simplified version can be turned into an open-ended game.
Error Detection Free your inner mathemagician! Mystify your audience! Give them lots of time to try to figure out what you are doing – you may be surprised by which student does figure it out. This game is based on one method that computers check whether transmitted information might have errors.</description></item><item><title>Futoshiki</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/futoshiki/</link><pubDate>Sun, 27 Jul 2014 19:59:27 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/futoshiki/</guid><description>Can you figure out the rules from this solved puzzle? 
getting started: check to see whether you understood the rules and see a partial solution to a puzzle classroom demonstrationfor teachers Futoshiki I – V puzzles to download Find many more at Brainbashersand Simon Tatham’s portable puzzles.</description></item><item><title>Domino bingo</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/domino-bingo/</link><pubDate>Sun, 27 Jul 2014 01:18:02 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/domino-bingo/</guid><description>Everyone seems to like bingo! Here are some variations that use dominoes. The game itself is appealing, gives students practice with addition and subtraction, and can form a good introduction to probability.
The gridscome in three sizes, using 9, 16, and 25 dominoes respectively. They are designed for 1″x 2″ dominoes. You can make your ownfrom the given template using construction paper or plastic foam.
I’ve played this with students as young as grade 2.</description></item><item><title>Pentominoes</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/pentominoes/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2014 21:35:53 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/pentominoes/</guid><description>Pentominoes have been around as puzzles for over 100 years, although they didn’t get the name “pentominoes” until 1953.
Each pentomino is made of 5 squares that are attached to each other on at least one side. Try to figure out what they must look like, then check to see you have all 12 pentominoes. They are named after the letter they most look like. Here is the set with their names.</description></item><item><title>Geometry</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/geometry/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2014 22:43:25 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/geometry/</guid><description>Geometry is a huge part of mathematics, although it often gets passed over in the school curriculum. Here are some great games and puzzles that help build geometric intuition. Some support more formal mathematical study as well.
Make two-and three-dimensional shapesfrom drinking straws. The three-dimensional shapes are particularly eye-catching. (Small hands will require some help with those.) You can also create towers using the straws – the most stable are built from triangles.</description></item><item><title>Other games</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/other-games/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2014 21:29:14 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/other-games/</guid><description>Here is a selection of other games and activities that involve mathematical thinking. While some are framed as puzzles, they seem different in kind from those in the Puzzles section. Some have many solutions, others are quite open-ended, leading to bigger questions.</description></item><item><title>Arithmetic &amp; algebra</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/arithmetic-algebra-games/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2014 21:24:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/arithmetic-algebra-games/</guid><description>15-Scratch and 24-Scratch are great games for almost anywhere you have a few spare minutes. You don&amp;rsquo;t need anything at all to play them, but it helps if you have something to write on and something to write with.
A more complicated version allows more operations and can entertain people for hours. If you write the numbers from 1 to 100 on a board with space beside each one, students can put up their solutions over several days.</description></item><item><title>Kakurasu</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/kakurasu/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2014 02:58:25 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/kakurasu/</guid><description>This puzzle is essentially a Latin squarewith addition. All you really need to know is how to add single-digit numbers, although subtraction is also useful. Once you’ve spend a few minutes sorting out which numbers mean what, you’re ready to start puzzling!
Can you figure out the rules from the solved puzzle?
getting started classroom demonstration 4×4puzzles (and solutions, just in case) 5×5puzzles (and solutions) 6×6puzzles (and solutions) puzzlesin three sizes Once you’ve mastered these, you might enjoy creating your own puzzles: just start with the tick and X-marks, work out the sums, then decide how many of the sums to give as clues.</description></item><item><title>Domino puzzles</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/domino-puzzles/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Jul 2014 18:06:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/domino-puzzles/</guid><description>These puzzles come in four levels. To make it easier to keep track within a level I photocopy the puzzles (double-sided) on different colours of paper, say puzzle 1 and 2 on blue, 3 and 4 on yellow, etc.
Level 1 involves only 13 dominoes. These are very popular with the K-3 crowd. Some children may need a little encouragement to get started: Which pieces do we know for sure?</description></item><item><title>On-line resources</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/on-line-resources/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Jul 2014 17:07:06 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/on-line-resources/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Hidato</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/hidato/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Jul 2014 23:41:27 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/hidato/</guid><description>This is one of most accessible of all the puzzles. All you need to be able to do is count!
It’s fun for primary students to have coloured counters to put in the blanks. This also reduces any concern they might feel about having a number in the wrong place, as it is very easy to fix.
introductory puzzlesfor primary grades (it doesn’t take long for these students to start demanding harder ones) puzzlesfor about grade 4 and up classroom demonstrations find more puzzles at the Hidatowebsite and, for primary students, at Math in English New!</description></item><item><title>For teachers: introducing Latin and Euler square puzzles</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/for-teachers-2/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2014 23:47:24 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/for-teachers-2/</guid><description>I give each student a baggie with 16 pieces: a square, circle, triangle and rhombus in each colour. Then I ask the students to sort out the pieces, without giving any suggestions about how to do that. If someone seems uncertain what to do in the face of the deliberately vague instructions, I ask them to figure out if any pieces are missing. That seems to provide enough direction to get them going.</description></item><item><title>Latin &amp; Euler squares</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/latin-euler-squares/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2014 23:46:09 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/latin-euler-squares/</guid><description>I love these puzzles! They are visually appealing, with bright colours and distinct shapes rather than numbers or letters; they require puzzlers to be very clear about which rules they are using; there are thousands of solutions for each level; and solutions can be found via many approaches.
Children are often quicker than adults at finding solutions,which makes them feel justifiably proud of their abilities. Even kindergarten students pick up on the idea, although you might want to start them with 3×3 grids.</description></item><item><title>Introductory Rectangles</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/introductory-rectangles-2/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2014 22:27:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/introductory-rectangles-2/</guid><description>I’ve used these puzzles with grade 2 classes (near the end of the school year) up to grade 4 classes.
 </description></item><item><title>Stores</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/stores/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2014 08:59:52 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/stores/</guid><description>Some good sources of mathematical/logical games &amp;amp; puzzlesRecommended by Susan Craving for a Gamein Central City shopping centre in Surrey; a good selection of puzzle-type games and a huge selection of board games
Dufferin Games Roomin Abbotsford; a fair selection of puzzle-type games, as well as many board games
Mastermind Toysin Langley and in Abbotsford; these have a moderate selection of games; on-line ordering as well</description></item><item><title>Rectangles I – VI</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/rectangles-i-vi/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2014 07:29:28 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/rectangles-i-vi/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Why puzzles?</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/why-puzzles/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2014 22:01:22 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/why-puzzles/</guid><description>_ _</description></item><item><title>Resources</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/resources/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2014 01:02:57 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/resources/</guid><description>There is currently considerable interest in developing logical/mathematical games, which is wonderful!
Best games: an annotated list of some of the best hands-on games that I’ve found. Some games are just better in physical form than on-line. The list is updated periodically as I find new games and try them out on people.
Stores:an annotated list of some stores in British Columbia which carry logical/mathematical games. If you know of a good store, please let me know so I can pass it on.</description></item><item><title>Other activities</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/other-activities/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2014 01:00:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/other-activities/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Getting started</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/getting-started/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Jul 2014 22:44:14 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/getting-started/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Rectangles</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/rectangles-2/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Jul 2014 22:07:40 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/rectangles-2/</guid><description>Can you figure out the rules of the game from its solution?
Rectangles connects arithmetic and geometry. For students who have already started multiplication and division this puzzle makes factoring tangible. For students who are just learning about multiplication, the puzzle provides a concrete introduction to multiplication as repeated addition.
getting-started downloadable puzzles for everyone from about grade 4 and up classroom demonstration for about grade 4 and up downloadable puzzles for (approximately) grades 2-4 classroom demonstration for (about) grades 2-4 Find more puzzles for younger students at Math in English, where they are called Shikaku.</description></item><item><title>Puzzles</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/puzzles-games/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Jul 2014 21:47:10 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/puzzles-games/</guid><description>Many of these puzzles need only paper &amp;amp; pencil, while others are physical. I use the brightly-coloured plastic craft foam for the latter. Look for it in dollar stores, craft stores, office supply stores, and department stores with a crafts secton. It takes a lot of careful cutting to make class sets – my mother has been a tremendous help!
Hover over the Puzzles tab above for a drop-down menu of puzzles I’ve used in classrooms and math fairs.</description></item><item><title>For teachers</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/for-teachers/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Jul 2014 18:22:04 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/for-teachers/</guid><description>Do not keep children to their studies by compulsion but by play.– Plato
Not everything can be learned in an atmosphere of play, but the more often we can bring effective play to our classrooms, the better! Students love it when they think they are getting away with something by playing games instead of doing “real” math. What they don’t realise is just how much mathematical thinking they are developing by playing these games.</description></item><item><title>Contact me</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/contact-me/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2014 00:24:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/contact-me/</guid><description>Write to me at susan@susansmathgames.ca</description></item><item><title>About me &amp; this website</title><link>susansmathgames/posts/about-me-this-website/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2014 00:13:25 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/posts/about-me-this-website/</guid><description>I taught post-secondary mathematics in British Columbia for 29 years, at Okanagan College in Kelwona for three years, then based at the University of the Fraser Valley in Abbotsford and Chilliwack for the remaining 26 years. Now I’m retired and living in Nelson, in the West Kootenays.
In 2006, I began teaching Math for Elementary Teachers and found that while some of my students could write the weekly quiz in five minutes, others took fifteen.</description></item><item><title>This is math?</title><link>susansmathgames/hello-world/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2014 22:16:59 +0000</pubDate><guid>susansmathgames/hello-world/</guid><description>We all know that mathematics is important, hard work, and very serious. BUT…it can also be a whole lot of fun. Professional mathematicians often admit to thinking of their work as extreme play.
Most people I’ve met love to hunt for patterns and solve puzzles. These puzzles, which have been enjoyed by thousands of people of all ages, are more than fun – they involve sequential and spatial reasoning, as well as logical arguments of many sorts.</description></item></channel></rss>